Okay, so we've learned how to create an app.
We've attached some reactive data. That was fun,
hopefully pretty easy to do.
And now, of course, we want to talk about
how we deal with user input, right?
Because that's what a lot of JavaScript's value is,
is handling the interactivity of your website.
So the first thing we want to talk about
is let's open Playground actually in Chrome.
So we have that.
So let me just open a new tab with this,
and this will be Playground.
Okay, so for the sake of Playground demo purposes,
let's just use the standard example of the counter app, right?
Which is the fact that if we go inside of here,
and this time I'm going to have, let's see, let's do that sequentially.
So I'll put a horizontal line here, line break, there we go.
And then here we'll just do an h1, we'll call it counter.
We have a count, and then we have a button
where we want to increment count.
This should look pretty familiar, 10.
Okay, so if you scroll down,
ooh, I don't like the fact that this is all the way at the bottom.
I'm going to actually move this up to the top.
Copy that, hr, great.
So we'll do this from most recent to oldest.
Okay, so here we have our counter,
and your question is probably thinking,
okay, how do we actually change data?
Because after all, it's fun to render some reactive stuff,
we want to do more with it.
So inside of view, we have our data here,
but the question is we want to actually change it.
And so the option that we want to learn about next
is the concept of methods.
And so if we think about functions in JavaScript,
right, typically we would have something like let count equals zero,
and then you'd have a function called increment,
and it would say count++, something along these lines.
When you think of methods, think of it as functions from JavaScript
that are available for your app to call at any time.
That's the best way to think about it.
So from this perspective, we would actually want to then define a method.
We'll just say increment count.
And inside of here, this is where a question that we had earlier comes into play.
So when you want to refer to something else in the app.
So in this case, we want to actually refer to this count property inside of data.
View is smart about a lot of things, but if we just currently say count++,
this is not going to work.
And the reason for that is because if we know when it comes to JavaScript
and programming, scoping is a thing.
So it doesn't know basically where to fetch count from.
And so this is where the dreaded keyword of this comes into play
when it comes to JavaScript.
The this keyword is where view basically takes the context of the app,
and it will basically figure out where count exists.
So from view 2, you might have noticed it from like this.data.count.
This would be an explicit thing you might do.
But because view knows that oftentimes we're referring to data or compute it,
it will, unless you have some really clear name clashes,
you can just use this.whatever property you're looking for.
And that goes for basically anything you're defining within this options API.
And the benefit of this is that while some people find that this keyword confusing,
the point of it, I think at the time when the API was being designed,
is around the fact that you shouldn't really have to think about what this even means.
The point is that I think of this as the app,
and that way you come in and you refer to this app, and that's it.
So when I was teaching other people view for the first time,
even though they didn't have a lot of JavaScript experience,
they got the convention that as long as I call this, it refers to my app,
and I'm not going to learn about scoping or anything.
It just works.
And that in itself is an advantage from a learning perspective.
But just know that you don't have to use this
so that in the future if people are actively avoiding it,
we can go ahead and do that once we learn about Composition API.
But while we're in the Options API right now,
this is how we actually refer to things within this configuration object.
Okay.
So now that we have the thisCount++, what we're going to do here now
is we're going to go and say, how do we actually call the thing?
And so what we're going to do is we're going to,
just like before, we're going to use a view directive to actually call the thing.
And so we're going to use v-on.
That is the directive that you'll want to learn for this
because similar to what you know from JavaScript events,
onClick, onKeyUp, this is the same idea.
We're extending on that theory.
And so instead of just like onClick, though,
which you might think that's what I'm probably going to guess,
view, because v-on itself is the directive,
you have the ability to pass it an argument through the colon symbol.
So it's v-on colon the event that you want to call.
And the event you want to call, again, is standard JavaScript events.
We haven't made anything up.
So key up anything that you can think of that's standard in the JavaScript API,
that exists.
And so when you click, what do we want to refer to?
Well, guess what?
We want to refer to our increment count function that we had earlier.
The key thing here to remember, though,
is that you don't want to actually call the function
because this is something that will be called when the event is triggered.
So basically you're passing a reference to the function inside of your app,
and then when it's clicked, it will be called.
That's the reason why you don't call it immediately.
So if we save that, and let's go ahead and now refresh our page,
you can see, boom, things are actually changing.
And they're being tracked.
So that's fairly straightforward.
What about something a little bit more complicated,
like what if I wanted to set the amount
that the counter is being incremented by?
Okay, well, in this case, you're going to say,
well, let's say we have a label here.
Let's say increment amount.
And then it'll be increment by.
And then you probably have some element here that's a number.
And then so if we refresh this, theoretically,
what you would want is the ability to change the amount
that increment count is changing.
So how would we actually do that?
Well, first of all, what we want to do
is we need a reactive data property
because we want to track what the heck is going on.
So at this moment, if we go down into our data,
we have this count, and we can say,
we can just have increment amount be a reactive data property.
And currently, it's one.
And then what we want to do then is tie it into our increment count down here.
Let me actually collapse this.
And so rather than just incrementing it by one, which is the plus plus,
we'll do plus equals this.increment amount.
And to show that this is working, I'm going to switch this over to 10.
And we're going to go ahead and refresh this.
And you can see it's jumping, as you would expect, by 10.
But we want to be able to change this, right?
How do we actually basically connect these two?
So let me go ahead and actually wrap this part in the div real quick.
Oops, that's not what I wanted at all.
Da, da, da, div.
There we go.
Okay.
That should give it a new line.
Perfect.
Okay.
So the first thing first is we need our input to display what it is that value is.
So how do we do that?
Normally, we would say value equals 10.
This is standard HTML.
But this is static, right?
This is something we define ourselves, has nothing to do with our app.
How do we connect the two?
The way we do that is with another view directive.
Because what are we doing?
We're now extending upon our HTML to give it super power to do what?
To have some interactivity, to be supercharged with reactive data.
And so you do that via vbind, right?
You're binding the value to a dynamic property.
That's the way to think about it.
But here, though, what are we binding it to?
We're not binding it to 10.
That's not what we're binding by.
We're binding it to increment amount.
So we can refer directly to the variable that we talked about earlier.
And so to show that this changed, this time I'm going to change increment amount to 8.
And if I refresh, boom, there we go.
We can see that they're now talking to each other.
And so now we can see when we increment count, this is great.
It's actually changing.
But what do we know about this?
We know that if we change now to 12, is it going to make a difference?
No, it's not.
In fact, it's going to reset itself back to 8.
What's going on?
Well, the reason for this is because you've told Vue, track this thing and make sure that
its value is always bound to this increment amount.
That's what you've told it.
And so this is why even though we've changed it once and we try to increment the count,
it's setting it back because that's what Vue is doing its job that you told it to do.
So what do we want to do?
We want to actually update increment amount whenever someone actually types inside of the input element.
So how might you do that?
Well, we're going to actually listen to an event.
And so what is that?
We learned it is V on, and we're going to listen to the input event.
And what we're not going to do, though, is we're not going to inline the function that will change this
because I find that to be very clunky.
So we're going to call it change increment amount.
And so what we're doing here is we're saying, hey, on the input event for this input element,
when we get an input event, I want you to run this function, which we have not created yet, to be clear.
So we'll come in here, and we'll go to a method, and we'll say change increment amount.
Just like that.
And here's the difference, though.
Now that you're actually listening to an event, you actually get a default event object
that's passed to you, once again, just like you would expect from standard JavaScript.
So I'm going to call that event.
And what we're going to do is, though, we're just going to log the event to prove that this is working.
So I'm going to go ahead and open this up, refresh.
And if I go ahead and type in here, anything happening, look, the input event is being fired.
So what do we know?
Well, we know, again, we won't dive into the details of it, but event.target.value is what you're looking for.
That's usually the convention for when you're playing with form elements.
So to show you this works, if I delete this, you can see it's actually showing up inside of my terminal,
as you would expect.
And so now that we're actually getting the dynamic value of the event,
we can then say this.increment amount is equal to event.target.value.
Now, to show that this works, we're just going to also,
I'm a big fan of, like, making sure things are actually working correctly.
So I'm going to go ahead and inside of here, we're just going to add a quick h1 for the increment amount.
So you can see here, we're rendering the increment amount here and here.
And if I change this now to 18, you'll see that it is being tracked correctly.
It's in here.
And now we can increment the count, and then, hmm, it's not working as correctly.
Anybody have a guess why?
String.
It's a string.
It's a string!
That's right.
So you might think, okay, well, you know what I'm going to do?
I'm going to come in here, I'm going to wrap this in a number, be done with it.
All right, let's refresh, let's make sure that works.
Let's do 80 this time.
All right, that works.
But I'll do you one better.
Instead of having to come in here and do it here, which is kind of silly,
because the increment amount, it already has a target value.
And what's a bit odd, too, is that, huh, if we look at our input element,
we are already typed number.
Why is that the case?
Well, this is one way to fix it.
Here's the thing, though.
If we take a look at our inputs, Sam had made the joke that I showed in the tweet
earlier that most of the web is rendering a list.
Well, I'd say a lot of the web is also filling out forms, right?
I mean, that's what a lot of our bread and butter is, too.
So Vue was like, okay, this is a lot of work to do every single time you have a form
element, right?
Like, oh, gosh, what if we could just learn from what Angular did
and do two-way binding in this particular context?
So instead of having to always define and change and track all this stuff,
what if we had a directive called vModel,
and we tracked it directly to the data property that we cared about?
Once you have this vModel, all of this, I say disappears,
but vModel is syntactic sugar for basically configuring all that underneath the hood,
which means that inside of our method down here, we don't need even the this as well.
So I can save that.
Now if we refresh, once again, let's do 800 this time and increment,
you'll see that things are changing just as you would expect with this vModel.
And what's even more interesting, if you'll notice, it's not a string anymore.
Because once again, what Vue tries to do is it looks at the developer experience
and it goes, hey, I know that I'm looking at an input element.
Because here's the thing, vModel works with other form elements like checkboxes,
radio, select.
You can do all that.
But it also knows what kind of input event to listen for.
Because you'll know that, especially with select, that one's a tricky one.
I always have to look up the docs every time I work with select.
I have to code it from scratch.
But here, it actually knows that we are a tight number in here.
And because of that, the value is actually tracking inside of its app
has automatically been converted.
Now if we did string, for example, here, or not string, text, revert,
you can see, oh, it actually is smart enough to even know what to do.
But the one thing I wanted to show, because this used to be a Vue2 thing,
is that you could actually attach arguments or basically modifiers to your directives.
So in this case, it's a vModel of number, for example.
But there will be other opportunities.
I'll get to present that later on.